Guide to the Miriam Frank Oral Histories on Lesbian, Gay, Bisexual, Transgender, and Queer Activists in the Labor Movement OH.039
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Gerry Faier, February 13, 1995
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 6-7)
    As of February 2025, second tape (#7) is missing.
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.036-037)
- James N. Green, January 10, 1997
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 132)
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 133)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 126-127)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.038-039)
- Jackie Harris, March 1, 1995
  This interview took place in New York City. Jackie Harris grew up in Brooklyn, NY as a tomboy with a heritage of union respect in her African American family. She was involved in the civil rights and black power movements in the 1960's as well as the March on Washington of 1963. Her first union membership came as a social caseworker in Local 371, DC 37 ASFSCME. Her interview covers the topics of racial oppresion, interracial relationships, social life with gay house parties, black people in the gay world, CORE activity, picketing Woolworths, Communist Party circles, her visit to Cuba in the early 1960's, FBI harrassment, activity in strike of 1967, division of work and social life with gay co-workers, promotions at job, her election as local delegate, and fiscal malfeasance in union hierarchy.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 11)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 12)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 11-12)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.040-041)
- Karin Hart, April 7, 1995
  This interview took place in Oakland, CA. Hart spent her childhood in Sunnyvale. Her mother was a teacher union activist and subscribed to the AFL-CIO newsletter. Hart was a student activist in the 1970's and became a phone company installer in 1978. Her interview covers the topics of strike strategies, high school lesbian consciousness, Briggs Initiative, climbing poles and support in nontraditional work, Central America and the CIA, Communications Workers union membership and stewardship, lesbian identity on the job and in Bay Area labor councils, social affairs, rural Califronia, gay/lesbian issues in unions, domestic partner benefits, CWA convention constitutional amendment 1984, later gay/lesbian caucus, Minority Caucus coalition, Cal Noyce's leadership, labor studies Antioch College, and the first Executive Vice President Local 9415.
  NOTE: This material continues in Karin Hart/Naomi Groeschel interview.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 36)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 37)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 36-37)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.045-046)
- Karin Hart/Naomi Groeschel, April 7, 1995
  This interview took place in Oakland, CA. Groeschel's mother was an organizer with the NYC Furriers in the 1930's. Naomi came out as a teenager and was active in the 1970 formation of the Union Women's Alliance to Gain Equality (Union WAGE). She was a local union steward and later a chief union steward of CWA #9415. Her ten year relationship with Karin Hart began with local union meeting and Christmas party. This interview covers the topics of lesbian identity in WAGE, repair and service jobs, Hart's election to Executive Board and then first Vice President of Local 9415, other lesbian CWA activist couples, and Naomi's Union WAGE work with Jean Maddox, Ann Draper, and Joyce Maupin.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 38)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 38)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.042)
- Ann Heler, April 28, 1995
  This interview took place in Detroit. Heler was a Wayne County teacher who received support from the leadership of Michigan Federation for Teachers for Gay/Lesbian Task Force. Her interview discusses the topics of the danger of women in trades coming out on the job in Michigan, homosexuality and teaching, her teaching of sexuality issues to people who were severely learning disabled, lesbian identity at workplace, Frank Colosanti gay high school counselor coming out in 1989, teachers' fears with gay/lesbian students, gay issues in union contract, closeted students, homophobic parents, state guidelines on sexuality education, union grass roots politics, being a single divorced working mother, coming out at age 40, lesbian/gay community organizing Ferndale 1990's, Michigan Gay Games delegation 1994, and right wing forces in local school politics.
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 63)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 63)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.003)
- Mary Kay Henry, June 8, 1995
  This interview took place in Washington D.C. Henry was raised in Arizona and the Detroit area. In high school she was an organizer for anti-hunger, college reproductive rights, and labor studies. She came out in the late 1970's and was greatly influenced by the UAW Women's Department and CLUW. Her interview covers the topics of hospital work, union training California SEIU, Elinor Glenn mentoring SEIU women, negotiations and lobbying Minnesota, emerging lesbian identity, coming out publicly and union policy, gay pride labor contingents San Francisco, Los Angeles, Minneapolis, balance of career/relationship, DC gay/labor organizing, health care reform and ENDA issues, living two lives, friends with AIDS in San Francisco mid-1980's, finding integrations with Local 250 AIDS committee, union as community center, Colorado/Oregon initiatives ealy 1990's, lesbian/gay labor politics, SEIU Lavendar Caucus, SEIU Health Care Division Director, restructuring health care and coalition work, labor movement heritage and social issue agenda, J. Sweeney and SEIU gay agenda and Stonewall Pride at Work conference 1994.
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 76)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 77)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 6, Audiocassette 76-77)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.048-049)
- Ruth Jacobson, March 6, 1995
  An alternate spelling for the last name of this interviewee may be "Jacobsen." This interview took place in Southampton, NY. Ruth Jacobson grew up in Holland and was a Jewish "hidden child" in World War II. She immigrated to NYC and trained as a typist, receiving her first job with the Girl Scouts. She came out in the early 1950's through the YWCA. Her interview covers the topics of 1950's social life in village bars and house parties, going to work parties with gay men, 1960's advertising art, sex discrimination, EEOC complaint, feeling normal about living a double life, long term marriages, anti-war work, breaking into the projectionist trade, Local 306 IATSE NYC, first female "boothman," gender differences and skilled work, mentoring influence of Steve D'Anzillo Local 306 president, her partner Jean LaBerge, acceptance of their relationship in union culture, and helping women enter the union.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 13)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 14)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 13-14)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.049-050)
- Ann Jochems, February 24, 1999
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 138)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 140)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.051)
- Walter Johnson, April 11, 1995
  This interview took place in San Francisco, CA. Johnson was a long-time advocate for civil and lesbian/gay rights. He was Secretary-Treasurer of the San Francisco Labor Council and a member and then the president of Local 1100 Department Store Employees (Retail Clerks) from 1957-1985. His interview discusses the topics of history breaking color bar, advancing gay workers in retail, gay men active in union early 1960's, promotion of gay arbitration, defense of cross-dressing/transsexual worker in the 1970's, educating members, domestic partner benefits, police raids, lesbian store workers, speech at rally for Briggs campaign 1978 and working with the gay community.
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 50)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 50)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.053)
- Marcy Johnson, July 13, 1995
  An alternate spelling for the last name of this interviewee may be "Johnsen." This interview took place in Seattle. Johnson was raised in Seattle in a railroad Teamster family. Her interview covers the topics of the Seattle bar scene in the 1960's, sexual abuse by her father, being selectively out at work, union member AFSCME, LPN supervisor, RN diploma studies, nurse union activist SEIU 1199 Northwest, district rank/file vice president, initiatives 608/610 Hands Off Washington discussion at Executive Board, Diversity Panel and coming out to 1199 delegate assembly 1993, homophobia, size discrimination, SEIU Lavendar Caucus, Stonewall 25 Pride at Work, Hands Off organizing and Seattle Gay Pride 1995 labor contingent.
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 100)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 6, Audiocassette 100)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.052)
- James Justen, June 28, 1996
  This interview took place in Kenosha, Wisconsin.
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 125)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 139)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 144)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.054)
- Gary Kapanowski, February 12, 2001
  This interview took place in Philadelphia, PA.
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 141-143)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.055-057)
- Cathy Kaufman, July 13, 1995
  This interview took place in Tacoma (Seattle). Kaufman was raised in Cleveland, OH in a union family involved with IBEW, UAW, APWU, AFT. Her interview covers the topics of class hardships, attending Catholic high school in the mid-1970's, Ohio Citizen Action corporate tax campaign, radical political scene, Toledo feminist community, seniors and low-key lesbian identity, NOW lesbian committee, other anti-homphobia projects 1980's, nursing home organizing SEIU #767, staff 1199 Northwest, health care politics, initiatives 608/610 OutFront Labor Coalition, gay/lesbian community and class consciousness, labor movement and gay identity, and Pride at Work.
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 101)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 6, Audiocassette 101)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.058)
- Lisa Kelly, April 29, 1995; cuid36287
  This interview took place in Toronto (Detroit). Kelly was not herself a lesbian but was an advocate for lesbian and gay caucus and a staff lawyer for the Canadian Auto Workers. Her interview discusses the topics of same sex benefits, the needs of gay/lesbian members in union apparatus, how lesbian voices emerged at annual CAW women's conference 1993, formation of caucus, top officers encouraging Gay/Lesbian caucus at Quebec CAW convention 1994, role of CAW Women's Department, involving gay men, cooperation of Canadian Public Workers, claims in Big Three Auto, developing policy grievances on gay discrimination, Big Three same sex spousal benefits negotiations, Canadian pension law, visibility problems, CAW culture, Canadian Labor Congress support of gay rights, her feminist childhood, law background and her commitment to gay family and friends and social justice.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Duration: 54 minutes
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 65)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 65)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd Oh.039.059)
- Darin Kinzer, June 14, 1995
  This interview took place in Washington D.C. Kinzer was raised in St. Paul, Minnesota. His father was in unions and had a liberal Farmer-Labor German Catholic background. His interview discusses the topics of Frontlash, early gay awareness, sensitivity to prejudice against Southeast Asian immigrants, Minneapolis/St. Paul gay newspapers, Frontlash Mondale campaign 1984, contacts with the Social Democrats USA especially Tom Kahn Assistant to AFL-CIO presidents (Meany and Kirkland) since 1972, Tom's mentoring/gay life, meeting Bayard Rustin, Sandy Feldman, staff SDUSA 1987, SDUSA structure, politics and ideology, Darin's intimate support while Tom was dying of AIDS, staff Free Trade Union Institute, homophobic harassment, hate crime lawsuit, front page story Washington Blade, widespread exposure in AFL-CIo 1991, Lambda Labor DC contingent Gay Pride parade, Stonewall 25 NYC 1994, and producing Tom's memorial at AFL-CIO 1992.
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 93)
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 94)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 6, Audiocassette 93-94)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.060-061)
- Connie Kopelov, July 14, 1994
  Historical/Biographical Note
  Connie Kopelov and her partner Phyllis Siegel were the first couple in New York City to be pronounced married on the first day that the Marriage Equality law took effect in 2011. Connie Kopelov's interview was the first of over 100 conducted by Miriam Frank as the groundwork for Out in the Union: A Labor History of Queer America.
  This interview took place in New York City. Kopelov was raised in Kokomo, Indiana and her college education and early career was dedicated to civil liberties. She participated in the labor education in the late 1950's through 1970's of the staff of the Amalgamated Clothing Workers of America and late District 1199. Kopelov was also an early organizer and staff member of the Coalition of Labor Union Women. Her interview touches on the topics of coming out, relationships, lesbian and social life in New York City in the early 1960's, necessity of self-censorship, union women, sexism, and sources of support and discrimination in the CLUW and ACWA.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 1)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 1)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.062)
  - Transcript (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Virginia LaGasa, July 14, 1995
  This interview took place in Tacoma (Seattle). LaGasa was raised in Southern California by her grandmother who was an anti-union bakery owner. Her interview discusses the topics of being a teenage lesbian, Hollywood bar scenes, heroin use and juvenile arrests, police harassment, alcohol and prescription drugs 1950's, street life, proprietor massage parlors, pregnancy and co-parenting, adoption of ex-lover's baby, factory jobs, motherhood in the mid-1960's, forced resignation LA County job, sobriety crisis early 1970's, finding lesbian support, Orange County NOW 1973, gay hotline network, awards for college work on chemical dependency, gay rights ASLU, anti-Briggs campaign late 1970's, group home counselor, union job Pierce County AFSCMe #53 state facility 1987, statewide AFSCME taskforce and other Tacoma gay/lesbian union activists 1990's.
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 104)
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 105)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 6, Audiocassette 104-105)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.063-064)
- Sandra Lara, March 21, 1995
  This interview took place in New York City. Lara grew up in a Puerto Rican/Italian family in a Jersey shore community. Her interview covers the topics of women's liberation, psychotherapy, butch identity, drugs and involvement in a spiritual cult, gender realtions on job, Ashram identity, being a member of CWA Local 1101, Marxist study group late 1970's, sexual harassment, sexist bosses, her election as a shop steward, 1980's writing for The Generator about political issues, AIDS training, strike activism in 1990 and gay identity at union conferences.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 15)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 16)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 15-16)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.065-066)
- Audrey Lehmann, April 8, 1995
  This interview took place in San Francisco, CA. At this time, Lehmann was described as a "young punk dyke" in her mid-20s. Her interview covers the topics of labor and queer consciousness, union family, factory work in union shop, safeway supermarket strike, conflicts with her brother about crossing the picket line, politics, sexuality and solidarity.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 39)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 39)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.067)
- Janice Loux, March 23, 1995
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Loux was raised in South Boston in a union family. Her mother was an activist in Local 26 Hotel and Restaurant Employees. Her interview covers the topics of her mother's sex discrimination suit of 1965, strike threats, progressive reforms, coming out in 1987-1989, personal support from Gay and Lesbian Labor Activists Network of Boston (GALLAN), work with members with AIDS, negotiating details of domestic partner and extended family benefits in union trusts, reform of Taft Hartley housing trust, grievance, coalition with ACT UP on AIDS discrimination, race and class issues in AIDS service, Local 26 record on gay issues, integration of union and personal life, and advice to other HERE activists.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 21)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 22)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 21-22)
  - Access CD (Box 1, Cd OH.039.068-069)
- Judy Mage, August 16, 1994
  This interview took place in New York City (New Platz). Judy Mage was raised in the Bronx, NY. In the early 1960's she held a job as a caseworker at the NYC Welfare Department, was an organizer of the Social Services Employees Association (SSE) and was a member of the Socialist Workers Party. Her interview touches on the topics of the conflict between AFSCME Local 371 and SSE, intergration of client advocacy, welfare rights, lesbianism, bisexuality, coming out into Village gay bars, Socialist Workers Party and faction battles, labor activism, union social life, her relationship with an union activist co-worker, SSE strike of 1964, her romance in prison with a Local 371 activist and her disillusionment with the welfare reform movement.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 4)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 5)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 4-5)
    As of February 2025, first tape (#4) is missing.
  - Access CD (Box 2, Cd OH.039.071-073)
  - Transcript (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Leslie Manning, April 10, 1995
  This interview took place in San Francisco, CA. Manning was raised in Rhode Island in an Irish-American carpenter union family. Her interview discusses the topics of NYC theater production gigs mid-1970's, NYC IATSE stage managers local, her move to San Francisco in 1979, activism gay/labor political scene, Labor Neighbor electoral education/action program 1994, Gay Freedom Parades, freelance mediation and fundraising work, early 1980's, producing of Democratic Convention Gay/Lesbian rally 1984, union labor at Women's Music Festivals, memories of gay activists committed to labor such as George Mendenhall, Gary Parker, Bill Kraus, Cleve Jones, Teamsters 921 newspaper driver job late 1980's, Coors boycott, AIDS and tricking among truckers, gay subculture, Teamster's women conference, open about her gay marriage in union, shop steward, Recording Secretary Labor Council delegate, 1994 SF newspaper strike, building gay/lesbian presence in newspaper unions, and community wide support for the strike.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 44)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 45)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 44-45)
  - Access CD (Box 2, Cd OH.039.074-075)
- Scott Melvin, February 27, 2001
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 148)
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 149)
  - Original Recording (Box Shared Tamiment 086, Audiocassette 150)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 128-130)
  - Access CD (Box 2, Cd OH.039.076-078)
- James Mitchell, August 11, 1995
  This interview took place in New Rochelle, NY.
  Tape #115: Mitchell was raised in Bronxville and his father was a salesman. This tape includes the topics of his parents' divorce, wartime survival 1930's, college fraternity scene and gay affairs, crisis over Episcopal vocation 1950's, homophobia and teachers, McCarthy, Greenwich Village, gay scene 1950's, GLF and AFT radicals, GAA 1960's, Fire Island cruising, NYC sex busts, Columbia Teachers, Social Studies certification 1960, Freeport JHS and racism and Jewish friends.
  Tape #116: New Rochelle community values, tenure 1966, gay identity, lover Walter Weeks MD, gay VD practice and holding drugs, army service, breakup and suicide 1967, student protests civil rights/Vietnam, teaching black studies, prominent academics in-service course late 1960's, Role of Supt of Schools, false AIDS diagnosis, district-wide AIDS policy 1986, being outed by colleague, NEA/AFT union work, AFT elected 1967, VP membership 1972, President 1981.
  Tape #117: union responsibilies, conflicts with management, high school burned down from arson 1968, differences with SWP union president strike 1969, NEA conflicts, teacher/civil service merger AFT 1979, gay/lesbian AFT caucus activits, homphobia and sex harassment grievance 1994-1995, AIDS information workshops mid-1980's, school board approved gay/lesbian student group and teacher workshop and troubled gay/lesbian teenagers.
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 115)
  - Original Recording (Box 9, Audiocassette 116)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box Shared Tamiment 095, Audiocassette 115-116)
  - Access CD (Box 2, Cd OH.039.079-081)
- Susan Moir, March 23, 1995
  This interview took place in Boston, MA. Moir grew up in a working class anti-union family in "Cork City," an Irish-American community. Her interview covers the topics of childhood lesbian feelings, bank and electronic factory jobs, women's liberation, hippy scene in San Francisco, drugs and street life, pregnancy, bakery production, Teamsters Local 629, early 1970's welfare, her enrollment in the University of Massachusetts, women's studies, coming out in feminist/socialist scene in 1974, cab driving, District 65 Paperback Booksmith warehouse organizing drive, alcoholism and sobriety, non-union school bus drivers solidarity, butch identity, involvement with Workers World Local 8751, lesbian union culture, bus yard harrassment and a brawl with a homophobe.
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 23)
  - Original Recording (Box 8, Audiocassette 24)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 4, Audiocassette 23-24)
  - Access CD (Box 2, Cd OH.039.082-083)
- Jim Monk, April 28, 1995
  This interview took place in Windsor/Ontario (Detroit). Monk was raised in Windsor in a Jehovah's Witness family. He received intense Jehovah's Witness training and struggled with his religious identity and outsiderness. His interview covers the topics of gay feelings and religion, his mother's schizophrenia, high school politics, an underground student newspaper "Thot," influence of feminist anti-war radical nun Pat Noonan, Windsor Labour Center, NDP "Waffle" factional politics, his bisexual sister, Chrysler truck assembly work, wildcat safety sitdown 1974, Johnsonite influences CLR James and Marty/Jessie Glaberman, UAW reps (Local 444), Raisa Dunayevskaya and News & Letters, Local 444 rank and file membership caucus confronting layoff politics, ostracism from closeted gay co-workers, gay scene in Windsor and Detroit, CBC-TV and sister coming out, CAW pro-activity on all harassment, comaprison of Canadian gay issues, AIDS service activism, Windsor school board election 1978, negotiating same-sex spousal benefits, gay contingent in Windsor Labour Day parade, and spousal benefits for Windsor casino workers 1994-1995.
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 61)
  - Original Recording (Box 7, Audiocassette 62)
  - Access Audiocassette (Box 5, Audiocassette 61-62)